Believe it or not
No matter how powerful an AI chip is,
it can still be hampered by “traffic issues”
Imagine that
you have built
the world's most powerful AI processor
with incredible performance
But when it tried to transmit data,
the data was stuck at the output
because its transmission speed
was slower
than its computation speed
It ended up like
putting a Mercedes engine on bicycle wheels—
the engine's strength was wasted
That's why everyone is going crazy
about a new solution—
silicon photonics
TSMC, NVIDIA, Intel,
Europe's PhotonDelta,
and Taiwan's ASE, LuxNet
are all racing to replace
electrical signals with optical ones
They even co-founded
the Silicon Photonics Industry Alliance
and the Heterogeneously Integrated Silicon Photonics Alliance (HiSPA),
committing to advancing transmission technology
in AI computing and data centers
But what exactly is silicon photonics?
Can it transform
the semiconductor industry?
or even challenge
Taiwan's advantage in this field?
Let's explore this revolution of
light-speed transmission in chips
because only by
understanding silicon photonics
can you truly ride
the wave of the AI era
To gain the upper hand
in the semiconductor market,
all semiconductor companies
are going all out
to develop chips
that are smaller and faster
In previous episodes, we talked about
how transistor sizes have shrunk over time
and how they'll shrink in the future
But besides transistors,
another key factor affecting a chip's speed
is the circuit for signal transmission
In 1959
the co-founder of both Fairchild Semiconductor and Intel,
Dr Robert Noyce,
proposed a new kind of integrated circuit
known as the monolithic integrated circuit
It integrated
every component of a circuit board
—including transistors, resistors, capacitors—
onto a single chip
There,
they were connected by metal wiring
through planar processing
This is the integrated circuit, or IC,
we often hear about
Semiconductor manufacturing technologies
and the IC concept
allowed us to shrink all components
along with transistors
As transistors shrink,
the interconnects between IC components
must also shrink
However, the thinner the circuits are,
the higher their resistance will be
This will lead to
signal loss and heat issues
In addition
the capacitance of the circuits also slows down an IC's response
Even if IC manufacturing technologies
keep advancing,
we'll eventually hit the speed limit
for electrical signal transmission
Moreover,
the rise of AI and IoT has triggered
exponential growth in
the demand for fast and large-scale
data transfers between chips
Companies providing services
based on data processing
such as OpenAI and Google,
need a data center,
no
multiple massive data centers
to process and store
data from all over the world
Data traffic in a data center
can be thousands to millions of times
greater than that at the end-user side
Accelerating the transmission of
internal data
is therefore a must
for high-speed computing in data centers
To boost transmission speed
between chips, servers, storage units,
and network equipment,
electrical signals must
be converted into optical signals
For the same reason,
we've already replaced
electrical internet cables
with fiber-optic ones
Using light for signal transmission
brings many advantages
including greater bandwidth
and longer transmission distances
In short-range transmissions,
optical fibers offer more than 10 times
the bandwidth of copper cables
Moreover,
optical communication can span
thousands of kilometers
For example, undersea fiber-optic cables
have very low signal loss per kilometer
Given this,
why not replace all circuits on chips
with optical fibers?
Why not supercharge transmission speed
and bandwidth to the max?
Because in reality, it's not that simple
A common optical fiber consists of
a core of transparent materials
such as glass or plastic,
and a cladding layer
of lower refractive index
This structure enables
total internal reflection,
allowing light to travel down the fiber
even around bends and corners
This works fine
for long-distance internet cables
but optical fibers are way too big
to fit on a tiny chip
So, how we can manipulate light on a silicon chip
using micrometer-
and sub-micrometer-scale components
is the central topic
of silicon photonics research
The good news is
while silicon absorbs light
with wavelengths below 1100 nanometers,
near-infrared light
used in fiber-optic communication
with wavelengths above 1100 nanometers
can pass through silicon
without being absorbed
This means
for light above 1100 nanometers,
traveling through silicon
causes no intensity loss
because of the silicon’s optical properties
So in principle,
with existing semiconductor
manufacturing processes
silicon waveguides
hundreds of nanometers wide
can be made on a silicon substrate
Similar to optical fibers,
waveguides are structures
for light to pass through
If such optical circuits
are integrated with electronic ICs
on a chip,
a smaller package will be required
and more data can be transferred between chips
What's currently used
in short-distance optical links
are the pluggable optical transceiver modules,
which have been in use for over a decade
In the module,
electrical signals from the processor
are converted into optical signals
by the transmitter optical sub-assembly
before going into optical fibers
At the other end,
the optical signals
are converted back to electrical ones
by the receiver optical sub-assembly
Optical transceiver modules
use traditional laser diodes
as their light sources
On the receiving end,
light signals must be converted
back into electrical ones
before going into
servers or networking devices
The whole process is like a relay race,
with the baton passed from runner to runner
You can probably understand,
this means there's still room to improve transmission efficiency
It can't keep up with the explosive data demands of the AI era
That’s why in terms of signal conversion
even though silicon photonics
doesn’t change the fact that electrical-to-optical
and optical-to-electrical conversions are still needed
its goal is to
integrate optical communication components directly onto chips.
This reduces the need for long-distance electrical interconnections
dramatically lowering signal delay and power loss.
It's like swapping congested city roadsfor high-speed bullet trains—
Data transmission will be
faster, farther, with less loss
To make this happen,
new photonic components
and packaging technologies are needed
With urgent demand on the rise,
the development of silicon photonics
is accelerating
A complete photonic IC
mainly consists of four components:
a laser light source,
a modulator that
converts electrical signals into optical signals,
waveguide components
to transmit and manipulate light signals,
and a photodetector that converts light signals
back into electrical ones
Right now
researchers aim to use
mature semiconductor manufacturing processes
to fabricate and integrate photonic components
on a single silicon substrate
and package them with electronic ICs
However
they ran into a problem in the very beginning—
the light source
A property of monocrystalline silicon is that
it possesses an indirect bandgap
So its light-emission efficiency
is extremely low
Simply put,
it cannot produce light
compound and alloy semiconductors
made from elements adjacent to silicon
on the periodic table
—groups III and V elements—
such as gallium arsenide, indium phosphide
and indium gallium arsenide phosphide
are direct bandgap materials
They are ideal
for making semiconductor lasers
So researchers have to incorporate
III-V materials or pre-made laser diodes
onto monocrystalline silicon substrates
through bonding or flip-chip processes
This is known as heterogeneous integration
There are several methods to do it
One is flip-chip bonding,
a method in which electrodes are made first
on a laser diode chip
Then the chip is flipped and bonded
By soldering or direct metal bonding,
it is connected to the electrical contacts
of a photonic chip
This creates a structure called
the "direct-attached laser,"
and this method is called
"hybrid integration"
While cost-effective,
it's harder to precisely align the laser diode
with the center of the silicon waveguide
Another common method
begins with building waveguide components
on a silicon wafer,
then bond the III-V material
directly to a photonic chip
After that
through etching, metallization, and passivation,
the III-V materials are made into
laser diodes
This product is called
the "heterogeneous integrated laser,"
or the "heterogeneous Si photonic laser"
The III-V materials
are bonded with the chip first
Then, the laser diodes
are aligned with waveguides
through semiconductor manufacturing processes
Compared with flip-chip bonding,
this avoids the trouble of picking
placing, and aligning laser chips
when integrating laser diodes and silicon chips
In addition to these,
one proposed method suggests
by first growing a virtual germanium substrate
on silicon
then layering
a germanium-tin alloy on top
Allegedly, this can also make laser diodes
Some researchers believe
these integration processes
are too troublesome
Why not just place the laser diode
outside the photonic chip
This would also avoid
chip overheating issues
Although each method of integrating laser diodes
with photonic chips
offers different advantages
for different applications,
heterogeneous integration
through wafer bonding
is currently considered
the most widely adopted and promising solution
for large-scale integration
Besides the light source,
another major challenge
in silicon photonics development
is converting electrical signals
into optical signals
Simply put,
to send information via light,
one should be able to use the “on”
and “off” states of light to represent high and low voltages
You might think this sounds easy
Isn't it just turning on the laser
at high voltage,
and turning it off at low?
Let's put it this way,
a direct modulated laser like this
has some inherent disadvantages
For example,
being directly modulated by current
causes a stronger photothermal effect,
wavelength shift, and other issues
And while the bandwidth of directly modulated lasers
can run over 10 GHz,
it's still lower than
that of external modulators
So what's an external modulator?
First, some context:
A laser diode emits a continuous light wave
when biased with a constant current
above its threshold
An external modulator is an optical modulator
that comes after a laser diode and
is controlled by an electrical signal
It in turn controls
the light intensity in a waveguide,
which means it controls
the “on” and “off” states of light
This is the optical modulator
currently used in photonic ICs
and they basically work like this
In intrinsic silicon semiconductors
—pure silicon—
a change in the concentrations of
electrons and holes
cause slight variations
in the refractive index
If a piece of pure silicon
is sandwiched
between a p-type and
an n-type semiconductor,
applying a voltage across the ends
can alter
the carrier concentration in the middle,
thereby changing its refractive index
But how does that help
switch a laser beam “on” and “off”
within a waveguide?
That's where
the microring resonator comes in
—also known as the “ring resonator”
Although such a ring-shaped waveguide
isn't physically connected
to a straight waveguide,
its ability to resonate with the light
determines whether the light
can pass through the straight waveguide
You see,
A ring resonator
has a certain resonance wavelength
When it is tuned to match
the wavelength of
the light in a straight waveguide,
a traveling wave resonance
forms in the ring,
thereby transferring energy from the straight waveguide
to the ring through coupling
As a result
no light remains in the straight waveguide
This corresponds to an “off” state
When the ring's wavelength
doesn't match the light's,
no resonance occurs,
and the energy remains in the straight waveguide
This corresponds to an “on” state
Now, remember that
the carrier concentration in the ring waveguide
changes its refractive index,
thereby tuning its resonance wavelength
So there's no need to change
the laser's wavelength
Instead, by putting
a p-type and an n-type semiconductor
on each side of a ring waveguide,
we can tweak its resonance wavelength
and modulate continuous light
The ring resonator
enables high-frequency modulation
in a space of tens of microns
In 2010
Intel used this design
along with the hybrid silicon laser
to launch a transceiver module
with a transmission speed of 50 gigabits
—or 50 billion bits—per second
It marked the commercial debut
of silicon photonics,
but that was more than a decade ago
So
how has silicon photonics developed
since 2010?
Many years ago,
Intel set its sights on
the massive data demands inside data centers
So it started investing in
silicon photonics R&D and integration
To this day,
it remains a leader in the field
In June 2024,
Intel introduced its first
based on the silicon photonics technology,
fully integrated
optical compute interconnect chiplet
co-packaged with an Intel CPU
It supports transmission using 8 wavelengths
on a single waveguide or fiber
Its bidirectional data transfer
achieves an astonishing speed of 4 terabits
—or 4 trillion bits—per second
Other major US players such as
Cisco, Broadcom, and IBM,
are also racing to catch up,
not to mention
the numerous startups and design houses
who all want a slice of the pie
What about Taiwan?
While Taiwan continues to lead
in advanced electronic IC manufacturing,
making photonic ICs doesn't require
cutting-edge nodes
such as 3nm or 5nm,
because photonic components
are significantly larger
So Taiwan doesn't have a clear advantage here
But companies like TSMC and ASE
have recognized
the rise of silicon photonics
In recent years, they've introduced
relevant integration and packaging solutions
In March 2025,
NVIDIA launched
a set of silicon photonics networking switches
that use
TSMC's COUPE packaging technology
—Compact Universal Photonic Engine
Each port supports up to
16 terabits per second
Via different port configurations such as
512 ports of 800 Gbps
or 2048 ports of 200 Gbps,
enabling an aggregate throughput of 400 Tbps
This enables AI factories
to connect millions of GPUs across sites
Moreover, TSMC's COUPE uses its own
SoIC-X packaging technology
to stack electronic ICs on photonic ICs
for maximum power efficiency
through vertical integration
In addition,
packaging giant ASE has introduced
the Fan-Out-Package-on-Package technology
as a new solution for
silicon photonics packaging
Although “silicon photonics” is a term
which has made headlines in tech news
in recent years,
the underlying technologies
have taken decades to develop
In the future
it could become as pivotal to technological advancement
as the transistor today
As mentioned
Taiwanese companies continue to push forward
not only in silicon photonics,
but in every field of
the semiconductor industry
From smaller process nodes
to brand new memory structures,
the semiconductor industry
requires constant innovation
As we enter the AI era
and look back on history,
it is clear that technology
wouldn't be where it is today
without the vision of Babbage,
the persistence of Shockley,
the boldness of the Traitorous Eight,
the leadership of Noyce,
the ambition of Morris Chang,
and the relentless efforts of countless others
Taiwan's silicon shield
is the result of generations of efforts
For Taiwan,
the semiconductor industry
isn't just a sector—
it's the backbone of
the nation’s strength
That's why it took us 14 episodes
to trace the roots and rise
of the semiconductor industry
In the future,
what breakthroughs lie ahead?
What technologies will emerge?
Whose names will join
the silicon hall of fame?
Hey, it could be yours
Don't sell yourself short
If you're curious about
the R&D of semiconductors,
please check out PanSci's channel
and subscribe
for more deep dives into the future of tech
This video series will end here,
but the race for semiconductors
is only just beginning
Thanks for watching
See you next time